Eh … this eh,
this first one we discussed before.
I didna get it on tape though.
It was a word for appearance, an appearance,
a sign of herring, maybe on the wing.
Appearance.
If you were hauling the wing of the net
you would see two or three [mashed/?] to it.
It was either a … coltas was it?
Aye [well/?].
Coltas…
[silence]
[XX] [You’re on aboot coltas/?]
Aye [XX] no mashed but then … aye.
A coltas.
What exactly was that?
The herring was [mashed/?],
when you were getting [mashed/?] herring, you know.
A [XX].
But that’s coltas again.
You know [XX] and the coltas, you know a sign of a puckle.
[XX] That’s the word that was only used for fishing.
You mentioned too this word puckle.
There was an Ardrishaig man didna understand what it meant.
A puckle?
Puckle, was that it?
Aye, that’s a wee puckle.
Maybe half a dozen or…
a puckle just…
a wee lot, a small lot.
I think there was one of the Ardrishaig men
had to have that word explained to him.
One of the Laws.
Aye, ’What do you mean like a puckle?'
‘What’s a puckle?’ he asked.
[XX] a puckle.
That’s as much as a puckle. [XX]
Who was that?
I don’t know [XX].
I wanted to explain it to you but that’s what it actually means.
A wee lot, a smaller lot and [XX]
That was one of the Laws?
It’s a puckle anyway.
Aye, Angie Law, Ardrishaig.
Was he a Gaelic speaker?
No, no, no.
Aye, he’d none of the Gaelic.
No Angie wasn’t [making oot/?]  the puckle.
‘What’s a puckle?’
Yes.
Are you familiar with a word [skaivin/?]? [Skaivin/?],
used of a gannet.
A certain dive of the gannet.
[Skeivin/?]
[Skaivin/?]?
Coming in at an angle, at a low angle.
That’s maybe a Campbeltown…
I think it’s similar to [skaitin/?].
Aye, that’s what it actually means, skeevlin.
They used that up here?
Aye, they used that, you know.
Coming doon to the herring and the herring,
the herring was [above/?] and just swimming along.
Skeevlin.
[Skeivin/?] would they say?
Aye, back and forward and [XX].
Was that [skaivilin/?] or [skeevlin/?]?
Skeevilin.
Skeevlin?
Aye… that was them and the herring,
you know just skeevlin,
coming doon at an angle to the herring.
Was that quite a common word up here?
Aye, quite common, aye.
Did they have any other words similar to that,
meaning, well, meaning the same thing rather?
No, I never- no.
Skeevilin, just going roond and roond,
skeevlin.
But what’s the meaning of the word, I couldn’t tell you.
Did this skeevlin.
Did that apply to the actual dive of the gannet?
Aye- that, they that called that up here [straikin/?].
[Straikin/?].
What exactly did skeevlin mean?
Skeevlin was just coming doon at an angle,
no’ up and doon.
Just the herring was on the top and just skeevlin over the water.
I see- aha.
Did you hear of any words for spent cod?
You know, like big… a big cod that was spent?
Aye, they called that here, a glipe.
A glipe?
A glipe.
Efter, they called it efter  [XX].
But mind you, what it means I don’t know.
I think it comes fae Gaelic.
What?
I believe it comes fae Gaelic.
Oh, it’s Gaelic- aye.
That’s what they call it, a [glipe/?].
But what the word means.
You didn’t hear of [droud/?] did you?
Eh?
A [droud/?].
I think that meant the same thing.
They use that in Campbeltown, a  [droud/?].
Oh, they might have a different name for it.
That meant just a spent cod. [Droud/?].
No.
No, that [XX] the glipe they always called it in…
mind you, I canna spell it.
Maybe get it somewhere [just/?].
Just leave that to me,  I’ll puzzle that yin.
Aye, a glipe.
As long as I’ve got it on tape.
And had you a word [sgaff/?]?
Eh [sgaff/?].
Staff?
Like a ‘g’ sound- [sgaff/?].
A [sgaff/?]?
Well we called them East coast boat skaffies [sgaffs/?].
No, this was… this was to do wi’…  wi’… the burning.
[I seen/?] a certain type of…
I think it was rubbish, wee fish and shrimps.
[Sgaff/?].
…on the surface. No?
No.
I think the Campbeltown men, they would see the…
Sìol, they called the wee herring.
It was either sgadan or sìol but never [sgaff/?].
[Sgaff/?]. That’s maybe a Campbeltown word again.
Now, I’ve a word here…
A sìol we called it, a sgadan or a sìol.
You would know them… in the water.
Eh, what was… what was maorach?
Oh, [you’re at the beach now/?].
Aye.
Maorach that was a wee… you know an eachan?
No’ a cockle but an eachan- smooth shell.
Now an eachan is like a cockle?
An eachan is smooth in the shell [XX].
A cockle’s [no’/?].
But the maorach was whiter and them sand…
where they were sandy [XX],
they were just drawn the ‘gether with the rake,
a bit like they do with the cockles.
You see the beaches, all them white shells roond aboot.
That’s all maorach.
They didn’t also call…
Used to get it in the Spring.
[Lovely/?] [XX].
Would the people have eaten them?
[XX].
All the [XX] on the [Kennay/?] shore there just [XX] of the shells,
white [XX]- maorach.
That was what they [XX].
That was similar to the cockle?
Aye, but smooth shelled.
Smooth shelled.
Smooth shelled [just like the eachan/?].
What was the difference between maorach and eachan?
The eachan, he was doon in the sand,
away doon and they were bigger.
The maorach was all the one size
in a white shell [XX] but a smooth shell.
Bigger the the cockle?
No, no, no as… it was longer but no’ as roond.
That was [what they called/?] maorach.
[XX]
[XX] That white shore was full of it too.
Was that also called maorach-bàn?
Maorach-bàn, that’s right, it was white.
Did you ever hear of that maorach-bàn?
Aye, that was the name they got, the maorach-bàn.
Now, they were… they were eating these?
I canna mind o’ eating it.
I ate the eachans whether that’s the same thing or not.
It was a bigger shellfish but smooth,
the same shape in the shell like,
but a heavier shell.
The maorach-bàn was quite thin in the shell but white.
That maorach, what was the reason for their gathering it?
They were taking it home for feeding- meat.
Aye, maorach.
How would they cook that?
Oh, that’s a [problem to me/?],
whether it was boiling or stewing it.
This was the Tarbert people?
Aye.
Would they go over on boats?
Yes, and they had the baskets on if they had to [cross/?] [XX].
They would walk the white shore and fill the basket.
That’s was the…
that’s what they were living on. [XX]
Was there a name for net mending or a net mender?
Net mending?
A local name.
Well, no,  just the mend, mending of a [repair/?].
You didna hear of cliùcain?
[No.]
That was just sticking, that wasn’t when you were working. [XX]
How, how, how, how …
Megglin together.
Megglin it together?
Aye, drawing it together, with a knot here and there.
That word megglin, what did that mean?
Just to [XX],
drawing it together
while the net was torn,
giving it time to mend.
Now that first word I mentioned, was that…
how was that pronounced? Was it cliùcairean or [cliùcain/?]?
Aye, well cliùcairean, [cliùach], [cliùin/?].
That’s the same again- just lacing together. Aye.
[Cliù-un/?]?
[Cliù-un/?] it together.
Or megglin it.
Just [anybody that needed it/?]
when you were in a hurry to get to the fishing ground.
Megglin aye. Megglin and [cliù-un/?].
[Cliù-un/?] aye, the same thing.
There was a word in Campbeltown…
…closing the holes.
…a net-mender.
They used to call a net-mender a cliùcair.
A cliùcair?
Cliùcair.
No, thon was just mending gear.
They might have had that right enough in [Kerrera/?] or Campbeltown- [cliùcain/?].
Can I ask you what was a…
I’ve asked you this before but I’d just like to get it on tape.
A sùgan.
Oh, a sùgan. I don’t know.
A net just when their…
and their length roond about or so many lifted to a post.
Four to every person [stretched oot/?].
That’s when they’re putting it but they want to make it stronger.
They take a fathom of the cord
and they tie that together wi’ a rope and
tie it in a stringer [XX].
That’s a sùgan, taking all the [white of/?] the herring on the bank.
That’s fine,  that’s a…
You know, just [wi'/?] a bucket and the stringer,
the sùgan and maybe a fathom of nets
[together/?] [XX] but tied wi’ a rope.
Did they ever use the word sùgan in connection wi’
just lashing up a tearing?
Aye, well that’s a [cliù-un/?].
That’s it, aye?
Aye, the same. That’s the same.
That’s the only connection you heard sùgan in?
Aye.
Did you ever hear an old net called a sùgan?
No, no.
That was [all the sùgan, you know/?]
[XX]or tied to the side
[for to take all the weight/?].
You’d have a fathom of nets
that thickness and a bit of rope roond and [XX] of stringer.
That’s fine.
That’s the only use of the word?
A person would never be called a sùgan like
a stupid person or...?
Aye, [XX] sùgan, they would say. [XX]
Was there another word for that?
Did you hear of a [torgean/?]?
A [torrigan/?] or a [torgean/?]?
No, no’ in Tarbert.
It was aye a sùgan: ‘You’d make a good sùgan’ [XX],
and they seemed quite secure, you know.
Did you ever hear of that word [torgean/?] in any other connection?
[Torgean/?].
No, it maybe, it must be Campbeltown again.
Eh, there’s one here, [ballicrubach/?].
Aye, [it’s related/?] again to a [cliù-un/?].
A [ballicrubach/?], that’s when you’re
free of the net
[XX] and you know,
take a sheep shank and the rope,
see and take your strain of it and that was, you know,
you could use the net when you got into port the next day.
You’re makin the net [wee/?] with a [ballicrubach/?].
A crupple?
A crupple aye.
Do you anything about this [balli/?]?
About what the first part of the word [balli/?] means…
I wonder?
I don’t know how that comes from, [balli/?].
I canna… canna get that.
[Crùbach] right enough.
[Ballicrubach/?], a cruppled bag or something.
I couldna place [XX].
No, it’s a kind of puzzle that.
That’s what they called it,
a [ballicrubach/?], aye.
A thing that was [XX] in the meantime.
Now, to come to lines.
What was stickin or stickin lines?
Oh stickin.
Aye, that was putting up the net.
You know in the [XX].
It was wool, that was what they used here.
But latterly on the [Sooth/?] coast they were using the string.
It was aye the [XX] we used.
What did stick mean?
Pardon?
Stick, the word stick.
Stick?
Well, sticking was, you know,
just running her through with a needle
for the time being, sticking her up.
But that was setting her up for the [XX].
That was making the net and how she was crupped and everything, you know.
They started when they were lifting four and [stitching/?]
two and a half and then you went out on the [XX]
and you lifted four and [stitching/?] out three. [XX]
You didn’t hear o stick in connection with lines at all?
Stick?
Stick lines, no?
Stickin the lines?
That was stickin the bait off them.
That was [smoorings/?].
You put them on the [pole/?] through the basket alive
and spread it [out with/?] the [pole/?]
[You were taking the/?] old bait off them, sticking them you know [XX].
That was stickin the lines.
That would, that would just apply to the stick pole, poling the lines?
That’s right.
[XX] Just, you put the pole across the two [sizes/?], you know.
That’s fine.
That was stickin the lines,
the small yins, aye.
Taking the old baits off.
[XX] it was [hair/?] or [snippen/?] they called it.
There was a [XX] to the back,
about a feet and a half and [they had/?] a feet and more ahead.
That was the line onto the back.
You, you mentioned that they used to twist that.
Aye, the hair.
With the fingers, aye.
[You’re talking half pounds/?].
I didn’t quite know.
I’ve got a detailed account fae you about that.
There’s just one thing I’m no’ very sure of.
It had to be a fella with [teeth].
Had it?
[XX] and then they caught it in his teeth.
[XX] asked how many hairs there would be,
he would get in his teeth and he would have a dozen or more hairs in his [netting/?].
They had an amount you know [he kept/?]
[XX] with the fingers in his hand.
Just about a dozen, was that normal?
That was making the [snoodge/?]
and then the hooks had to be tied to it after it was [snoodged/?]
and then there was a fella [twaddling/?].
When he [twaddled/?] to the end,
he would just put a knot in and tie it to the knot.
Now, the man that was plucking them out the [sock/?] with his teeth,
he would pass the…
The hair.
He would put a knot in and pass it to the fella that was [twaddling/?].
And he would twirl up everything?
Twirled it right up to the end and put a knot in.
And when [XX] they would pass each other,
the other fella,
and put the hook on and cut that knot off.
[It was in then/?] and then tap the hook on to the [netting/?].
It wouldna… for the man that was twisting or twirling the, the hair,
he wouldna split it in two, no? He would just… twirl up the whole thing?
No, no, he split it in two and just twirled it.
So, there were actually two [snippens/?].
But the twist [XX]
Oh, I see, aye, aye.
You see, he would twist the two
and when he let them go they would curl up themselves
and he would just put a knot on.
He was just making the one [snip/?] though
but it was cut in two to make it [XX]
That’s right- they were [cutting/?] the two.
That’s fine.
Now, I’ve a few words here for
big shots of herring.
Eh I wonder, I think you’ll know some of them.
Eh like you know there’s a good shot in the net,
maybe a boat coming along going by,
shouting ‘What have you got there?’ I’d say ‘I’ve got a good…’
something or other.
Can you mind any of these expressions?
There’s one of them I got ‘A good steall’.
That’s one of them.
Were there any more you can think of?
Just along the lines of, you know, a steall of them.
A steall?
I’ve one here.
It’s maybe just Campbeltown. A sleever.
A sleever. Aye, oh that’s Campbeltown.
You didna use that?
[XX]
You didna use that here at all?
I couldna [handle/?] a sleever.
That wasn’t used by the Tarbert men?
No, no.
A [tapaidh/?] o them.
A tapaidh. A good tapaidh.
A tapaidh?
No? No.
That’s Campbeltown again.
A glàm. A glàm o them.
No, no, no, no.
That’s Campbeltown again.
Are you familiar with the word [misleach/?].
Eh, the word [misleach/?]?
[Misneach/?] Aye, that was used in Tarbert.
I know that there’s no’ much [misneach/?] here.
There wasn’t much sign or there wasna much hope.
[Misneach/?] that’s,
I can gie you the explanation of that one.
If there was a good sign, a good [misneach/?] here,
you know, but if it was the other way
‘There’s no much o’ the [misneach/?]’.
You didn’t hear it in connection with a mess, maybe a net?
No, no, just the signs or, the signs- good signs or no signs.
There was [misneach/?] or no [misneach/?].
What about a dràbhag?
That’s to do with quantity again.
A dràbhag?
A dràbhag aye.
A dràbhag was a fella that was keeping them back.
Aaah.
Aye, a dràbhag.
No use.
[That’s what that would mean/?].
‘You’re only a dràbhag.’
Aye
Aye, that was, that was referring to the man.
There’s no connection with gear, though?
No, no.
Sorry, no.
They used to use it in Campbeltown in the sense of,
[mibbe/?] you would put the net in and there was very little.
Just a, a wee scatter and they would say ‘Oh, there’s only a dràbhag.'
A dràbhail.
A-ha.
A [dribble/?], aye.
Well, no no.
Just, I think it’s pronounced the same as the word you gave me.
Just a, like a dràbhag.
Or some of them would say a [dràbhach/?].
A dràbhag or a [dràbhach/?].
That’s a Campbeltown word, that one.
Well…
A dràbhag, if you mentioned that,
that was just a man.
‘You’re only a drabhag’ you would say.
That’s right.
Aye.
Did you hear of [gadrach/?]? [Gadrach/?].
Eh, rubbish.
[Gadrach/?]?
Eh, like eh [gadrach/?], [gadrach/?].
You know ‘What did you get?’
‘Just a lot of [gadrach/?]’-
shells and seaweed and just useless stuff. [Gadrach/?].
No, no.
It must be Campbeltown again.
Aye, that’s Campbeltown, aye.
It was a lot of [XX] and [ruffians/?] [XX].
Did you hear the word [truisleach/?]?
Or similar to truisleach, just for trash.
[Truistearach/?] or truisleach? No, it must be…
No, that’s [a new one to me/?].
What about bùrach? A bùrach?...
A bùrach, I don’t know.
But burraidh. [XX].
That was [XX].
But that wouldna be [it/?].
What was that, [burraidh/?]?
A burraidh, a burraidh.
A [XX], you know, a bragger.
That’s [what they said/?] ‘You’re only a burraidh.’
That wouldna be [it though/?].
Somebody that would be bragging and…
Bragging, aye.
That was alluding to himself and the way he carried on.
A burraidh. A [burray/?] as you would say.
What about neònach?
Neònach?
Aye [now/?] that’s useless again - stupid.
Neònach, kind of half-hearted.
Aye, they’re [XX].
Neònach - useless I would say it meant.
Did you hear the expression galar-plocach…
or anything similar? Galar-plocach.
I think it means mumps.
I’ve heard the name right enough but what it means.
Galar-plocach.
Aye some, that’s some, some kind of disease.
No, it wasn’t much used, bar by the old, old ones.
Galar-plocach.
That’s right in your throat, swallowing your glands.
Aye, that’s what they called it, the old men.
That wasna in the fishing then - that was more an illness, galar-plocach.
When you had a sore throat, you know, that was that one.
There’s some of these are, they’re a…
I’m getting more on to ones that aren’t
directly connected with fishing, just general words.
Eh, left-handed? A word for a left-handed person?
Ciotach/?].
Of course I couldna spell it even.
I’ve got the spelling all right.
It’s [ciotach/?].
Aye, I’ve got the spelling.
Left-handed.
Did you ever hear o corrie-handed?
That’s the same.
[Ciotach/?] and corrie-handed.
Did the old men use corrie…
Aye, there was a fella in [XX],
[Ciotach/?], [he was/?] left-handed.
His left hand was better than the right.
Duncan MacLachlan?
Duncan MacLachlan.
[Ciotach/?], that’s what he got.
A [heated/?] man though,
he made them models you’ve ever seen and he had [XX] to his hands.
Aye he was about, he was a carpenter [helper/?], I think.
Oars again, he made [XX] oars, [put/?] a block over it.
Now, that’s another one, the oar.
Was there a local name for that?
The oar?
Ah-ha.
No, an oar.
You never, you didna hear a ramh?
No, oar we did it on.
Oar?
Aye, in my time.
A-ha.
Eh.
The stern oar, that’s what we would call it.
That, eh corrie-handed, was that used in Tarbert
by the old men?
That was [ciotach/?]
and the very odd time it was, it was corrie-handed.
[Ciotach/?]
You know when they were describing.
[Ciotach/?] was the main one?
[Ciotach/?] was a left-handed man.
‘He was [ciotach/?].’
Oh, they used that right enough.
[They named so much/?].
In fact [Ciotach/?] [XX] got his name
through that - he was left-handed.'
Did you hear, are you familiar with a word buinneach?
Eh, buinneach.
[Bruidhinneach/?]?
Eh, buinneach. Buinneach.
Oh, that’s a cabbage runt, a buinneach.
That’s a...?
A cabbage runt, the stalk o’ a cabbage.
A buinneach.
That’s a [XX].
I couldna describe what buinneach means but it’s Gaelic anyway.
That’s what they called the cabbage [runt/?] - you know,
the stalk of it.
That’s what they call it.
There’s a strange word here, eh,
used in Campbeltown - maloogrum.
Maloogrum.
No? It’s maybe used in…
I’ve heard that name right enough.
They mibbe say ‘The best of maloogrum.’
What it means, I don’t know.
Or ‘That’s the real maloogrum.’
[XX] an expression in Gaelic.
Maloogrum.
I think it’s somehow connected wi’ drink.
I think so.
Stuff they used to make, I think.
Aye, could be right enough.
I think [XX] that’s where it originated - maloogrum.
Did you hear it in Tarbert?
Aye, I heard it in Tarbert - aye
and that’s where it was connected.
The stuff they were getting in distilleries.
You canna just think of an expression it was used in?
No, just maloogrum they called it.
You know they would be aboot the distilleries
and get a half bottle of maloogrum.
There’s another word here which seems to be connected with distilleries.
I wonder if you’ve heard it - [kilogie/?].
[Kilogie/?].
[Kilogie/?]?
I believe it was a type of stove.
[Kilogie/?].
The [bogie/?]?
No…
eh, [kilogie/?].
No, it was [bogie/?].
They called the stoves in the old boats [bogies/?] but no’ [kilogie/?].
[Bogies/?], aye.
[Bogie/?].
It was just a tar you got after that
and [everyone was calling it/?] the [bogies/?]
You would see [XX] tar so,
an [asp/?] and just eh…
Aye. This was the stove before the [XX]?
Aye, the [bogie/?],
that’s what they called it-
the fire.
Oh, they used that often, aye.
The latter years [XX] of tar, you know.
That was like a wee range.
Aye, that’s fine.
Are you familiar with the word [railleach/?]
[Railleach/?],
in connection with the weather maybe.
You would say ‘It’s [railleach/?] the day’.
No? It must be Campbeltown again.
I think it just means rough, wet or windy.
No.
[Railleach/?].
No, it wasna an expression roon this way.
Was there a word up here [muilleans/?]?
[Muilleans/?].
[Muillean/?]?
[Muillean/?] or [muilleans/?] or [muillidh/?] even…
I think it was wee crumbs or wee bits of anything.
They called them [muilleans/?].
Meelins?
Meelins- aye that, that  might be another, aha.
Oh, I’ve heard the word meelins?
That’s anything mashed up- meelins.
‘There’s [empty/?] meelins’,
[empty/?] small bits, broken up.
Meelins, aha. I couldna spell it right enough.
No, don’t worry about that.
Oh, I heard that often enough.
What eh, what connection would it be used in?
What would it refer to?
Anything that could be broken into stour just- meelins.
Anything, aye?
That’s the way they would express it:
‘It’s broken in meelins.’
You know, munched up just.
‘[XX] meelins’
that was the way they would express that.
[XX] broken- anything that’s in meelins.
Oh, I’ve heard that often and oft.
Was there a word for a bend, maybe like a bend in a bow spring?
A bend?
Well, then a sweep, you know, if there was a bend in anything.
That’s what they called it- [XX] a sweep.
[XX] or anything like that- there was a sweep on it.
Was there a sweep [XX]?
A bend, aye.
They didn’t use the word [cam/?]? [Cyam/?] or [cam/?].
[Calm/?]?
Well the [calm/?], that was [an everyday word
for a quiet still of water/?]. [Calm/?].
No, I think that’s English.
This is… this would be Gaelic for a bend.
They use it in some of, it used to be used in Campbeltown with a [cam/?] in the bow spring,
a [cam/?] in the [XX] , or a [cam/?] in a pole.
But it was sweep that was used up here.
Sweep. They possibly mean the same,
just the same-  a bend.
Could I try you wi’…
A [cam/?], aye.
Could I try you wi’ sgliùrach?
Aye, that’s what, that’s what I’m expecting for that to [XX],
you know, useless.
[Sgliùrach/?].
[XX]
Oh, I heard that one.
Are you familiar with the word burgoo?
Burgoo?
That was more or less
a kind of by-word for thin porridge or…
that’s what they did [XX] burgoo.
Was that used among the older men?
[Kind of/?] porridge, aye.
Did the old Gaelic speakers use that word?
No, no’ our ones.
The later [XX] simply gave burgoo for the porridge.
Aye, thin porridge.
That wasna an old word, no?
No, no, that’s a later title they gave it or some [branch/?]
that dinna like it or something.
Burgoo they called it, the thin porridge.
What was the old, the old name for porridge?
Aye, the brochan.
Brochan, the porridge.
[XX] of whisky.
That’s the way they would take it,
the old Hieland men.
Whisky?
Aye, [XX] be whisky.
There was whisky in the porridge?
Aye, that’s what ye call,
that what do you call it-
Lord Lovat’s soldiers used to get it?
Oh, Atholl brose.
Atholl brose.
The whisky and the meal.
Did you see that, did you see that done?
That’s what it came oot of, the name Atholl brose.
That’s what it is, a neeffel of meal and ordinary whisky.
Have you seen that done?
No’ me, no.
But that’s what they were living on when [they were away from home/?].
Did the Tarbert ones used to do that, aye?
Did they used to do that in Tarbert?
Well the old ones, some of them would.
That’s where it originated.
You had so many soldiers, you know,
at that time.
They had to keep so many, them landowners.
That’s where the name originated, Atholl brose.
You didna hear another Gaelic name for that,
that kind of whisky?
No. No’ here.
That kind of porridge, rather.
Eh, the word [pook/?]?
Pook? Pook.
Oh, that was here, aye.
You know, when you’re pooking a hen or a bird…
No, I’m thinking of something.
That would just be, I think that’s just Scots for pluck.
Pluck, aye- plucking a hen or pooking the hen.
No, I was thinking if a boat would bring up, maybe a boat towing,
would be towing a [trawler/?] and
she would snag on something and she would gie it a pook.
Have you heard it in that connection?
That was more [used/?] in Campbeltown.
Was it?
Aye. A wee [stringer/?] and a pook.
A wee pook and a rope and [stringer/?]
wanting to go ahead you know,
tighten it up.
That wasn’t [XX]?
No, it wasna [XX].
And they used to use that too when they were fishing.
They would feel a [pook/?]
A pook that’s right.
Did they use that here in that connection? No?
That was when you were fishing a line,
you know an outward line
and you would have a pook on a hook,
a [chug/?] as you would say.
Was that common here, aye.
Aye, you would hear them there, the young ones, when I was young -
‘I’ve got a chug, you know, on a hook in the bay.’
What about a pook? Would they say a pook?
A pook. Aye, they would. Aye, that’s right.
Would the older men use that?
No, no- the younger ones [XX].
So, that wasna an old word…
No, [XX].
They never did much with a [XX].
[It was all small yins/?] [XX].
Now, there’s a word here that I’m interested in.
It applies to a big kind of sea.
A [drug/?] or a drog.
A drog? That’s … well,
that’s more or less surf,
you know, coming on the [XX] on the beach.
You’ve seen it [XX]
a kind of heavy swell that comes up the [XX]
and [droged/?] back and dragged back.
That’s what they called a drog.
Was that…
…was that used here?
Aye, oh, I’d say it was a heavy [drog/?] on the beach down there.
That was common used…
That wasn’t applied to…
…efter a gale.
…a long lazy swell?
No, no. That’s just from the beach, the drog.
The beach- to run up and then come back.
A drog.
That’s how they pronounced it,  a drog.
A drog, aye.
You would say there was a heavy drog [in/?].
Were there any other words applied to
the motion of the sea that you can remember?
I’m thinking of English equivalents like jabble or…
or bound.
[XX] A bound, well.
Were there any Gaelic words you can remember?
No, just a bound, just a heavy bound.
[XX].
Or a jabble, just the way you’re saying it.
A nasty jabble [or/?] a nasty bound
[but the drog was/?] on the beach you know…
I see, that’s interesting.
…after a gale o wind or strong breeze.
Just more or less surf
[but they had it in/?] drog.
That’s fine.
Aye, I think that’s…
I’d better no’ let the fire out.
No.
There’s as much [difference/?]  between here and [XX], as would do [XX]
[...]
Aye, they’re lovely expressions.
[XX] and they had all that,
more or less, and in Campbeltown and all.
The heavy drog… after a strong breeze.
You didna hear the old men when you were young
using the expression a pet morning?
A pet morning?
Well, no, it was in later years
I heard them talking, you know
[XX] ‘it’s only a pet [XX].’
What did that mean?
You know, it was a good [morning/?] but it wasn’t going to last.
Was that, is that English, do you think?
English, aye. A pet.
You know, it was good for a start but
the day was going to be [XX].
A pet.
Did you hear of [caingeachs/?]?
Or maybe…
I’m giving this as a Campbeltown pronunciation. [Caingeachs/?].
[caointeach/?]?
Had they that in Campbeltown?
Aye.
Oh, I couldna spell it mind you.
No, don’t worry about that.
I know [XX].
You tell me what it meant up here.
That’ll, that’ll dae.
It’s a… I was with them, mind you, that was seeing it [XX].
I was trying my best to see the [caointeach/?] but no.
I know a case of [XX].
This one fella,
he was seeing this wee wife on the [hill/?].
He gets them all there to turn back
and they turned back and they couldn’t see it, like me.
So, it couldn’t be it-
it must have been something that was implanted in their mind.
That’s the way I put it.
I’ll tell you the name of [them/?].
There was big Sandy Jones, a big fella, aye he was six feet and more.
Well, he was only young at that time, aboot over 20,
[XX] his mother and uncle.
He belongs in [Spinyside//] doon there,
and one o the sons, sons married in
[XX]'s daughter in Campbeltown.
During the Spring tide I was going home,
well, I lived doon the Battery
and they were going up the brae,
the two o them
and I don’t know what they seen but
they came on up to the gatehouse.
I left the two of them at the gate
and they were shouting [XX].
And they were seeing whatever it was but
[not the heck/?] I could see.
And the brother, for some reason,
it was on the hill and the big men, five or six,
he made them turn back, come all the way back like.
’Oh, it’s a wee [witch/?].'
The wee wife was seemingly greetin'.
And they couldna hear it or see it but still he was seeing it.
[XX] I heard it on the wireless wi',
what do you call that singer and comedian?
Val Doonican.
The wee folk in Ireland.
Well, at least when I heard Val Doonican
it just came back to me like that.[XX].
[XX] like me. He couldna see it.
That was the [caointeach/?]?
The [caointeach/?].
Seemingly it was a [true/?][XX].
You’ll no’ hear it now.
When you would hear that and a certain
lot of people there was somebody going to die.
That’s an old tradition here?
Aye and that was right.
That [XX] was right but
could I see it, no, or hear it?
Did you ever know that, eh prophesy?
[XX] Pardon?
was that, eh, sign ever...?
I’ll just change…
[...]
[XX] but I could see [XX].
But they say the older brother would be seeing it
and hearing it and everything.
That’s them going to a well for a drink
and he got, he got the 5 big men to turn back.
Aye, frightened of his life
and they were seeing nothing like me or hearing nothing.
They were going up to a well?
To a well, going for a drink.
You know Jacob’s Well [XX]?
No, Jacob’s Well.
[XX] Place you go every
Sunday, especially in the summertime. [XX].
Have you any idea how it got that name?
Oh, I don’t know, it’s…
that was [it/?] as far as I could mind.
Where aboots was that?
Way over just above the Columba Hotel on the hill.
Up in the [face of a rock/?].
But there were…
you know [XX]
made a round of stones roon it
and a run oot so it wouldna overflow.
Oh, it was as clear as crystal.
When you went up there
for a mug of water on a Sunday if you were dry.
In fact the last time I was over at it,
I was looking, there was aye a dish, a cup or a tumbler
and I was feeling in the heather,
a full bottle of beer in the heather.
[XX] pretty good.
They must have left it and put it back [XX].
Some [lad/?] was up and
when he [used/?] a drink of the water he couldna drink the beer
and he put his [jug/?] in the heather.
Whether he got it or no’, I never spoke to him.
Is the cup still there, aye?
The cup, aye. There was aye the cup.
Just a metal cup?
Aye.
Well, they used to look efter all that in the old [XX]
if they had time somebody would clean it out
to get rid of yon green.
Was there an old word for a kettle or a teapot
you can remember?
Teapot?
Aye.
Well the teapot, the kettle.
The [North/?] [XX] ones had the Gaelic for it
but no’ here. Just the kettle.
Kettle. Teapot.
The kettle and the teapot.
Was it strùpag they would, strùpag they would say?
Strùpag?
Strùpag. Strùp.
That was the [supping/?] the kettle,
you know the [supping /?] the tea.
But you know, we just got the teapot.
They used that here, strùpag?
Aye,
but up in [Barra/?] there they called it [XX] a [currag/?],
oh, aye.
A [currag/?].
That’s what they called it- that was the Gaelic.
That was up in [Barra/?]- [currag/?].
The rock ootside o… [Barra/?].
Oh, the [curragan/?].
The [curragan/?].
That’s the same thing.
Is that the wee, the wee…
The [curragan/?], the kettle.
The [XX] as you go into Northbay.
They call it the [curragan/?].
The [currag/?] they had o it.
The rocks, the [currag/?].
Was there a word up there bus … bus?
A booth?
A bus.
Ah well, that was more or less a shelter,
a wooden shed or a… a booth.
Oh no- it’s a bus, like busach.
A bus.
Oh, that was unpleasant again, a [gurner/?]- busach.
A [woman/?] you can never please, busach.
[A bit of a gurn/?].
[Oh, that one/?].
Was there a word mùgair? Mùgair.
[Bugair/?]?
No, like … no,  an ‘m’, mùgair.
Mùgair?
Mùgairing aboot.
Mùigean, aye.
Aye, mùigean.
Aye, there was that [XX].
What was that?
Mùigean- [Mixing/?] among you know any,
you know any kind of dirty stuff.
Mùigean: ‘Don’t be mùigean about it’.
Aye, you know
mixing it up, mùigean.
But the busach was that, a gurn [XX].
Never pleased.
Busach you called that.
Oh, thon was [XX].
What about falachan?
A falachan.
I think that applied to a hoard, maybe a hoard of money hidden.
Something that was found , hidden and maybe found.
No?
Found, no. [XX]
I’ve two similar ones here.
I wonder if you might recognise these:
a ghealachan or a gealachan?
A dealachan, well that’s, that’s a light.
A dealachan.
Aye, a light… or the moon.
Dealachan.
Oh that, well right enough, gealach for moon.
That’s right.
They also used… they also used that for a light?
That was, that was in everyday use.
[XX] ghealach.
This word gealachan, did that apply to a, a lamp or?
No, I never heard that [one/?].
Just the moon?
Just the moon,  [the/?] ghealach.
There could have been that in some other…
There wasnae a word for the noise of gulls? No?
There wasnae a word for like a,
a gathering of gulls, the noise it would make?
Of gulls?
Well no,
no’ in particular.
[I would say/?] there were plenty of gulls and that
but the Sooth coast, well they had a coil of gulls.
A coil.
Aye, a coil.
They’d be sweeping around/?],
they were seeing the herring although we couldna see it.
A coil of gulls.
[XX] but [no one/?] around us.
That was an Ayrshire word.
That’s fine- that seems to be everything.
Aye they had, they had the gull coil.
It might hae been [XX].
You’ll find coil in [coil/?] of gulls.
[...]
A coil they called it, you know swirling aroond in a circle.
You didna hear of the kildee?
Aye, I heard of kildee but what it is.
It’s a wee fish.
You used to get them in the [smoorings/?]
Many a time I strung a dozen of them on a string and
got a bob or more [stringing kildees/?].
You know they were better than whitings
but they were only wee, about that size.
Only on the west loch you would get them a [XX].
About a foot…?
You see they would never take them off-
they were just thrown on the top.
I used to go through the top for the kildee.
[String them up but/?] […].
They weren’t [XX] among the other fish at all.
That’s what they called them, kildees.
Now is that an old one?
That’s an old one.
The old men in your youth used that word?
It’s them that used it, kildees.
But you’ll never hear it now.
Well, they use it in Campbeltown now…
Do they?
At the fishing we talk about kildees, aye.
You’ll no’ see them,  [XX] clear of the land.
Aye well, at the trawl like, at the trawl.
Do you get them?
Unless that’s maybe…
Well you, the next half a dozen, you try and keep them.
You’ll never try better.
Well that’s…
They’re no’ very big, you know.
Kildees that was just, they were wee.
I think that’s the origination of the name,
they were wee fish, kildees.
I think so cos they were never very big.
Big eyes though.
Big eyes.
Aye, it must be the same ones.
That’s right.
Red in colour and the kind of heavier strip [around/?].
They’re more like a John Dory
only on a wee-er scale.
The same kind of rough scale on them.
Oddly enough I was in the, I was in the company of eh…
That’s the kildee then.
There’s another fish… eh,
was there a name,
I think it’s another name for the John Dory,
a local name.
Can you remember that?
Johnny Dories.
Was it Jacob something? No, it wasn’t, no’ Jacob.
Something haddy?
Oh well, the John Dore, you know-
Johnny Dory we call them here.
John Dore in the [book/?] [XX].
No, you were telling me…
I tell you what it was.
It was when Eric [Cregeen/?] you know the Manx man,
was in. Remember?
A-ha.
We came together.
He was talking about a type of fish they use to fish for
in Tiree and they,
they had the same name in Tarbert.
You said they used to get them wi’ lines, fish for them wi’ lines
oot o Tarbert.
Hake?
No, no it was a fish that’s no’, it’s no eaten now,
well it’s no’ caught hardly.
I think it was the John Dory but it’s something haddy.
Gurnard?
No, that will be the ouden or the cnòdan.
Aye, cnùdan.
That was our name- we called it cnùdan.
A gurnard’s the right name.
We used to fish them up in the [XX] burn there.
Aye, cnùdan.
Cnùdan.
That was, when it was, when you would touch it,
it would give a growl.
You would feel it,
you would hear the kind of syllable of a growl coming oot it.
Cnùdan was our name for it but the right name is a gurnard.
There weren’t talk about eh…
It’s a very stabby fish.
…cruchan, cnuchan dhearg?
I believe there were red ones and blue ones.
They wouldna distinguish between the two, no?
Aye, they were red and blue.
A-ha but they didna distinguish between the two in language, no?
No, they were just a cnùdan, aye.
You would get red ones and blue ones but it was all a cnùdan.
They kinda gurned right enough when you went up to them [XX]-
you would feel the vibration itself in the fish,
but a very stabby fish.
They used to fish them in dry wood barrels.
You would get four or five shillings to pack them.
Dry them?
Dry wood barrels, you know the half-wooden barrels.
Did they fillet them first, aye?
No, they were just put in the way they fished them.
They were getting [XX], I think there was five shillings for [drying/?] the barrels.
This was the Mull men?
Aye, fishing them up there at Duart, up that…
They’d be using like wee ring nets?
A ring net, that what they were using.
You mentioned a word there eh,
I’m interested to know whether it,
whether it’s an old word,
whether you can remember the old,
the old men using it when you were,
when you were a young man.
Eh, a touch, a touch, you know, a fine touch.
You know if you got a good shot, you would say a fine touch.
A touch, aye.
Is that an old one?
That’s an old one.
[XX] touch [by the old men/?].
Touch they called it.
You’ve no idea what that is?
I’ve no idea what the…
‘Aye, we had a good touch the day.’
[Coming from the boats/?], you know [XX].
It sounds English but whether it’s English, I don’t know.
Well, the old men had that, aye.
It doesn’t make any sense as English.
They had it up here and back.
Oh yes,
when I look back and they had it
‘we had a good touch’ before me,
that’s over a hundred.
The men’s a’ deid but
many time I heard them mention the touch-
‘We had a good touch the day.’
Oh, them- that was [them/?],  the touch.
Oh, you didna hear of the [hass/?],
the [hass/?] or [has/?]?
It’s just a word I heard in Campbeltown.
It’s a wee class o herring.
Hally?
Eh, [hass/?]- [hass/?] or [haws/?].
It’s herring, they’re bigger than sile but they’re
no’ big,  the hass.
No, no- I havna been in touch wi’ that one.
That must be Campbeltown again.
Aye, it must be a Campbeltown.
Naw, that’s just about it.
Fry, there were herring fry, you know,
wee herring, sile.
No, it winna be that.
Sile, soil they call them now [XX].
Soil?
Aye, they’re wee wee, only the length of your wee finger.
There’d been millions coming ashore on the beach wi’ the piuchdaidh chasing them
and then put them ashore on the [wreck/?].
And I seen the same thing in [Southern/?] [Italy/?].
A big boat bursting wi’ them alongside the quay.
There wasn’t a sile to be seen
and the [XX] coming in together to all the rubbish and
alongside the pier inside o her was
like silver wi’ wee herring jumping out to get clear o,
all the rubbish was just like silver right along the pier,
with her coming in but she was [buckling/?].
Aye, I used to take stock o’ all that.
Just the same as here… aye.
I’ve seen me up, I’d be near over the bows o’ the boat.
It seemed to me big herring [playin’?],
oot in the middle of the [Mediterranean/?].
Oh millions of tons o’ it,
[solands/?] and gulls [XX].
But eh, but herring I was taking it to be.
Oh, there was a sea of it just.
We were st-, sailing through that for half a day.
Maybe pilchards or something?
It was clear, shining in the sun
but it jumped just like a herring.
But I seen them [XX], aye.
But thon was oot [XX] efter leaving [XX].
The [XX] was coming near the net o it.
No, this is fine.
No, take that.
Oh, that’s, that’s a wee [XX].
Take the half o it.
No, no, no.
Cut a half. I’ll get more.
No, not at all.
Well take a…
This is fine [XX].
Aye, that was in a lake, Lake [Tumshall/?] I think it was.
You know there were fresh water lakes [XX].
Plenty of [trout/?] if you could,
well you wouldn’t get…
Take a wee bit off it.
Oh no, no, no, no.
Aye, just a couple of smokes.
But I’ll bet you there were
hundreds of tons of fish on them.
They were [XX]
That’s the gannet?
The gannet, sollan goose, aye.
Was that the word the old men used?
That’s the sollan.
The sollan.
That’s the one they [XX].
You’re no familiar…
That’s seemingly the right one, the sollan goose,
and that’s what they called them, the sollan.
Of course that’s more a Campbeltown, gannet.
More a Campbeltown, the gannet.
The [XX] on the Sooth coast of Ayrshire,
the [Southern men/?], the sollan.
Are you familiar with the word smùrach?
Smùrach?
Aye, that’s breakin’ anything into dust, stour.
You know, anything that kind of crumbles into smùrach,
wee bits.
That’s the same as millean, milleans?
That’s right, the same thing- smùrach.
You didna hear that in connection with the weather?
Wetness of the day, no?
A smùrach day, no?
Smùrach? Aye, [they had a word like that/?] right enough for the weather.
Can you remember it?
No, [just as I said/?], smùrach.
Kind of smùrach, you know kind of wet, showery.
A-ha. That was the word?
They had that word right enough.
That was the word, eh?
But that said you could use it for brekkin’ it into smùrach,
that’s into dust or…
I wonder would that be like eh,
would that be like small rain,
like kind of fine rain?
Small rain, kind of smùrach.
Oh no, that’s right enough.
That’ll be just like the English smir, I suppose?
Smir, yes but they had it smùrach.
Smùrach, that’s fine, eh.
And then you can have the smùrach, brekkin’ it into smùrach.
That’s into wee [pairts/?] as small as you can [break them/?].
Smùrach.
And they had that in the weather,
kind of smùrach, like wee rain.
Aye, that’s fine.
Eh, what about the word pluc? Pluc?
A fluke?
Eh, a pluc. A pluc.
Pook?
Eh, pluc. You know, the pl, pluc. A pluc.
A pluc in your face you maybe would say.
A pluc, a pimple.
A pimple, aye, that’s fine.
It seems to be the Gaelic again.
That’s what they called the pimple, a pluc.
Aye, aye you’re right enough,
a [plucaidh/?] face.
Aye you’re right enough aye,
that’s how it originated.
You didna, did you hear of a word,
I’ve heard it in Campbeltown
and it seems to be from Gaelic although it’s been corrupted.
Eh, I’ll just say it as I heard it.
Eh, [throuither/?], [throuither/?].
[Strutharair/?]?
[throuither/?].
Eh, I’ve heard it like, like through,
like th-, [throuither/?] - a [throuither/?] person.
No? Kinda difficult, a difficult boy or mischievious boy,
they would say was [throuither/?].
A [throuither/?],
a [throuither/?],
a [throuither/?] [XX].
A [throuither/?] boy, no’ well-behaved,
you know kinda difficult you would say.
[throuither/?].
You, you, you are familiar with that?
Eh?
You’re familiar with that word?
Aye. Oh, that was a quite common word,
[throuither/?].
As the old folks would say ‘You’re a throuither boy ‘[like/?].
You know cheeky or forward or difficult.
No’ well behaved you would put it.
That’s fine.
That was throuither.
You know, that’s no’ so old at all.
But they had it, the old ones, right enough.
Did you hear o the word [gàint/?]? [A gàint/?].
No? Someone with a [gàint/?] in his speech.
A [gants/?]?
A [gàint/?]. A [gàint/?].
You know, a [gàint/?] in his speech.
A glam?
Eh, a [gàint/?]. I think you might have…
it’s kinda difficult to,
eh, like a, you know, a [gàint/?],
like a stammer, a stop in his speech.
No?
Was there a word up here they used for a person who stammered
or stuttered?
A stutter.
Oh, yes,  aye that was [bad/?] in a funny way,
kind of tongue-tied.
You’d a stutter- you know you’d have [XX] and stopping.
You would tat-tat-tat.
[XX]. Oh, the old ones had that.
Was it just stutter they said?
A stutter.
They hadn’t a Gaelic word for it?
No, just a stutter.
Eh, you didna hear o gagach?
They had gagach, you know but that’s one in the same thing.
Kind of gagach, stuttery.
Oh, they had that, they had a’ them ones.
I think that’s aboot everything.
That was the stutter, gagach.
Aye the time has changed- you never hear the words.
You never hear them.
Gagach.
It was [XX] and the dug was through there
and would be looking at you.
He’d be thinking you were cracked.
Just finally, there wisnae a word for eh, herring dirt?
No,
at least I never heard o it.
You didna hear o salach?
Salach?
Salach.
Well salach was wet, you know.
That’s what they would call it when it was wet or raining heavy.
‘[XX] salach’, if it was wet.
But the herring dirt they would just name that herring dirt.
Salachair, no? Salachair.
I think I put that one- no, I think I asked that before.
I’ve never heard a name like that.
It’s just dirt they would say?
Herring dirt.
They were leaving that behind them you would say.
[XX], oh just like [croy/?].
That’s fine. I’ll…
That’s when it was going away, aye.
It was aye leaving that behind it.
I’ve seen it myself often-
you would lift it with the pail
and the herring would be leaving Loch [Fyne/?] and getting away.
Why would you lift it wi’ the pail?
You know, it was that thick-
the water was absolutely red wi’ it,
it was red in colour.
Well, sort of pinky red.
I’m surprised they hadna a word for that, apart fae dirt.
There must hae been a Gaelic word at one time.
Oh, they would hae it among themselves, aye.
No, the herring dirt I always say.
The likes of [the older/?] [class/?] would have a word.
The word sgadan, that was used, was that used quite a lot?
Och, the herring, aye,  that was
every, in everyday use, the sgadan.
Sgadan saillte, is sgadan gréine is sgadan frìos.
What was that third one?
Eh?
What was that last one you mentioned?
Sgadan gréine.
No, the one after that.
Sgadan frìos,  the fresh herring.
Frìos, aye?
Aye.
Oh, among themselves they would,
that’s all they would use for a herring, sgadan.
[XX] in the Gaelic.
Sgadan frìos.
The sgadan gréine,
the sgadan saillte and that’s no’ right Gaelic either.
Salt herring right enough but seemingly it’s no’ the right,
the [XX] you know,
that’s what they had it on, salt herring.
Did you use the word roochle up here at all, eh?
Roochle?
Roochle.
Well, a roochle, aye.
I’ve used that an odd time but…
That wasn’t an old word here, no?
No. No, that’s a later one.
A-ha.
Och well, I’ve done no bad.
I suppose I’d better, I suppose I’d better head, head home.
Oh [XX].
Well it would pass the time.